[SPEAKER_01]: How to practice noble silence?
[SPEAKER_00]: By not engaging in any distracting behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: By practicing wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything that you discern that it's rooted
[SPEAKER_00]: In an unnecessary desire to distract yourself, to take your mind away from your present situation and your mindful of, that's basically against the practice of wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's also important to note, it's not like... you don't need to be forcing your mind, like, I'm present, I'm present, because you're present whether you want to be or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: Loss of mindfulness, loss of wakefulness, all these things are rooted in basically unwholesome intentions, which means you cannot become unwakeful, non-wakeful, if you don't engage in any intentional act based upon greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind... mind's intentions are not rooted in any of the unwholesome things, then you cannot be unwakeful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already a noble silence.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean you never speak to anyone, or you never, like, do anything whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you just don't do things that are rooted in desire, or, like, greed, aversion, or distraction and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why is it silence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you call it silence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind quiets down.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the mind is distracted, the thoughts, the verbal thoughts, the kind of dialects, it's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole dialectical thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, once you haven't been... and again, people are trying to stop this thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't stop the thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can quiet it down by seeing... Basically, the thinking, the loud thinking, so to speak, is a symptom of your lack of your proper restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not restraining your mind in a proper manner, in a sense of not delighting
[SPEAKER_00]: In, in, in lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Resisting delusion, resisting aversion and engage, and engaging in distraction and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start discerning that, that's what quiets the mind down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't go, oh, I'm on my mind quiet, I focus on my nostrils and I'll be quiet.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you just fall asleep, most likely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or go in some state of, like, focused attention to something, where, but again, you just lose, lost awareness and mindfulness completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is no different than if you fell asleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to see, basically, that the problem is not in you not trying hard enough to be in the present moment, which is, again, not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is you not understanding the nature of intentions enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not understanding them, you don't know when they are rooted in greed or aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just guessing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you guess it right, sometimes you don't, but you don't see that, which means you're wrong, for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind will quiet down,
[SPEAKER_00]: When the physical restraint and sīla has been developed, the verbal, you know, verbal actions are kept in check, and then, mentally, you just don't give... don't give in to the, like, presented options of sensuality or aversion or distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't... just don't give in to those.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they are not those, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to be always be mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are already mindful by not giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already mindful because you're already abstaining from certain types of mental intention, which are the unwholesome types.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, things you don't do, that's what becomes your present activity, in that negative sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's not on a level of doing or on a level of technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be doing the abstaining from these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's just discerning certain things that you won't be giving in to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, everything else that's not those things, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha, even when he was sort of instructing minds how to understand the jhāna, establish the mind in jhāna, he would say, he would say then, don't, don't like fear every pleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they had the attitude of whatever's pleasant is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, it's, it's, it's, it should be, it should be dismissed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they were interfering with things they shouldn't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's agreeable and not rooted in desire, aversion, delusion, it's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you assuming that that should go away, well, it's you overstepping your jurisdiction, you interfering with that which is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some people might think that locking themselves into a situation of solitude, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: No distraction, no TV, just being like a prisoner, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going to jail, solitude, solitary confinement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people in that situation go mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, if a person knows what they're doing, as in, they understand the nature, they can discern the nature of their... that, indirectly, the nature of their intentions, they can see when they're rooted, then, yes, solitude will just result in further clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would encourage monks, provided they already had the right view and establishment in sīla, in restraint, to go in the in the jungle and remote dwellings, to not socialize even with other monks and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't have that knowledge,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, well, again, you might sort of use it while keeping a notion in your mind that you must develop knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes people forget that and then they try to get the circumstances to do the work for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, I'll go for a three-month retreat to Burma in a kuti and people will just bring me food and I won't see anyone and so on, thinking that that kind of extreme solitude will sort of result in freedom, enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can only support the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't have the knowledge,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just staying in the solitude and you will not necessarily learn from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if the solitude would always result, then yes, exactly, that solitary confinement prisoners will all be arahants, arahāngamis.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they are not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's been away from confinements, away from unwholesome intentions, long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's knowledge of what defilements are and unwholesome intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what frees you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being away from them is necessary, to an extent, to start discerning that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you have no notion of what that knowledge is, no amount of being being away from those defilements will uproot them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If anything, it will just conceal them further, because now you don't really don't know where to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, your strength being
[SPEAKER_00]: The restraint being the necessary basis, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And usage of solitude to use it to gain the knowledge, not to use it to avoid the circumstances that bother you and you don't know how to deal with.